Office of the President Mary Maples Dunn Files, 1985-1995
Smith College Archives
Office of the President Mary Maples Dunn Files
1985-1995
Dunn, Mary Maples.
RG 32 UUID:315e6fea-90dd-4979-b8d9-d655a20dfdcd
198 boxes (82 linear ft.)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
Smith College president from 1985-1995 whose administration created programs, wrote position papers, and adjusted college policies and structure in order to deal with the questions of race and sexuality. Dunn dealt with the budget during an economically troubled period and began the process of getting the college on the "Information Highway." Includes incoming and outgoing correspondence, reports and working papers, newspaper clippings and photographs.
Mary Maples Dunn was Smith's president from 1985 to 1995, an economically troubled period for the college. But the imbalanced budget was just one of the challenging issues she faced during her tenure. Campus diversity, internal communication flow, and socially responsible investment were also significant issues during her presidency. However, Dunn maintained a cheerful image and a sense of humor throughout, and persevered through the trials of her difficult position.
Dunn took office in 1985 after seven years as an administrator at another of the famed Seven Sister colleges, Bryn Mawr. In fact until that point nearly the entirety of Dunn's academic career was spent at Bryn Mawr. After she received her undergraduate degree from William & Mary in 1954, she went on to Bryn Mawr to do her graduate work in colonial U.S. history. She began teaching at the college while she was completing her Ph.D. then moved through the academic and administrative hierarchy until she became Dean of the Undergraduate College in 1978 then Academic Deputy to the President in 1981.
When she arrived at Smith the first order of business was to work on her fundraising skills. Development became a significant part of the duties of the President during Jill Ker Conway's tenure. Dunn immediately set to work on enlarging the college's endowment and locating funding for several new initiatives. The battle to balance the college's books included two capital campaigns, an increase in tuition, and a number of structural changes. Alterations in employee benefit packages and offers of early retirement had a significant impact on the college staff and caused considerable distress in the community. But while scaling back in some quarters of the campus, Dunn also had to fund necessary progress. Physical changes included the construction of Bass Science Center and the Young Science Library, and a number of renovations to residence houses. She also began the process of getting the college on the "Information Highway." The internet was first introduced to campus during her tenure along with e-mail and voice mail.
As Dunn was preparing to leave the college she reflected, "It's true that acquiring budgetary accountability is among my most important achievements, but I hope I'll be remembered as a president who helped open the college up to a more diverse population." Some of Dunn's most well-known challenges were related to diversity. South African divestment was a source of much conflict on campus when she first arrived, and a few years later inadequate office space for the multicultural organizations on campus reached a fever pitch. Dunn also had to deal with continuing publicity and institutional attitudes about Smith students' sexuality. Throughout her tenure Dunn was repeatedly forced to address media coverage of Smith, Northampton and the "L-Word." Her administration created programs, wrote position papers, and adjusted college policies and structure in order to deal with the questions of race and sexuality. The most extensive program, the 1988 Smith Design for Institutional Diversity, dealt primarily with race, but other endeavors handled questions related to sexuality, physical disabilities, and derogatory language.
When Dunn left Smith 1995, she went on to become director of the Schlesinger Library on the History of Women, then interim president of Radcliffe College and acting dean of the Radcliffe Institute for Advanced Study. Dunn left the Radcliffe Institute to become Co-Executive Officer, with her husband Richard, of the American Philosophical Society in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. They retired from that position in July 2007.
The Dunn Files include approximately 82 linear feet (198 document boxes) of material dating from 1985-1995. Some material has been restricted according the College Archives policies. The open records (99 document boxes/ 41 linear feet) include incoming and outgoing correspondence, reports and working papers, newspaper clippings and photographs. For more specific information about the contents of the collection see the series descriptions and folder listing below. See the Subject Guide on pages 9-11 of this finding aid for a list of topics of a broad nature.
Subject Guide
The Subject Guide is meant as a supplement to information provided in the Series Descriptions and Folder Listing, and is in no way intended as a comprehensive listing of significant subject matter in the collection.
Academic Programs Funding Sources
-Ada Comstock Scholars
Series V. Administrative Offices
-Development-Corporations
>-Connecticut National Bank
-Philip Morris
-Development-Foundations
-Aetna Foundation
-Dr. Scholl Foundation
-Starr Foundation
-Valentine Foundation
-Community College Connections
Series V. Administrative Offices
-Development-Corporations
-Chemical Bank
-Connecticut Bank and Trust Company
-Connecticut National Bank
-Northeast Utilities
-Warner-Lambert Company
-Development-Foundations
-Aetna Foundation
-Balfour Foundation
-Donaldson Charitable Trust
-Freeman Charitable Trust
-Roche Relief Foundation
-Sprague Educational and Charitable Foundation
-Stackpole Trust
-Surdna Foundation
-Current Students / Future Scientists and Engineers Program:
Series V. Administrative Offices
-Development-Corporations
-Bay State Gas
-Bull HN Information Systems
-Citicorp
-Honeywell Bull
-New England Electric System
-Northeast Utilities
-UNISYS
-Warner-Lambert Company
-Development-Foundations
-Norton Company Foundation
-Shell Companies Foundation
-Dual Degree Program
Series V. Administrative Offices
-Development-Corporations
-Analog Devices
-Combustion Engineering
-Hoechst Celanese Corporation
-Honeywell Bull
-UNISYS
-Development-Foundations
-General Electric Foundation
-Shell Companies Foundation
-Smith Summer Science Program
Series V. Administrative Offices
-Development-Corporations
-Citicorp
-Development-Foundations
-Balfour Foundation
-Shell Companies Foundation
-Surdna Foundation
Affirmative Action:
Series IV. Administrative Issues
-Diversity
Series V. Administrative Offices
-Affirmative Action
Series VI. Alumnae
-Individuals. There are a number of letters from alums asking about the topic, and many variations on the same response from MMD.
Series II. Academic Departments
-Religion & Biblical Literature for April 1988 letter to the Sophian and May 1990 report on Smith Design
Series XII. Faculty & Staff
-Equal Opportunity Employment and Grievance Procedures
-Minority Faculty
Lesbianism:
Series IV. Administrative Issues
-Diversity
-Lesbianism
Series V. Administrative Offices
-Admissions-General. Scattered throughout are concerns about losing prospective applicants due to rumors and media coverage
Series VI. Alumnae
-Individuals. There are a number of letters from alums asking the question, and many variations on the same response from MMD.
Series IX. Committees & Boards
-Community Policy, Committee on-General for 29 March 1994 letter from MMD addressing the issue of same sex benefits.
-Diversity, College/Alumnae Task Force on
Series XI. Events
-Otelia Cromwell Day, for panels addressing homophobia
Series XVII. Students-Unrest-Diversity (1992-1993)
Race:
Series IV. Administrative Issues
-Diversity
-Racism
-South Africa
-Town & Gown Relations-Civil Rights Advisory Board
Series VIII. Colleges & Universities
-Swarthmore. For info regarding June 1987 conference entitled " The Recruitment and Retention of Minority Students in Liberal Arts Colleges."
Series IX. Committees & Boards
-College/Alumnae Task Force on Diversity
-Community Policy, Committee on
-Race/Diversity
-Task Force on South Africa
-Senior Staff, for 12 April 1993 agenda item regarding Rodney King verdict
-Space Allocation Committee-Student Cultural Organization Space
Series XI. Events
-Conferences
-Civil Rights: Institutional Diversity
-Encuentro de Latinas
-Experiences of Black Students
-Otelia Cromwell Day
Series XII. Faculty & Staff
-Minority Faculty
Series XVI. Speeches
-All-College Meeting on Race (1 May 1989)
Series XVII. Students
-Unrest
South Africa:
Series IV. Administrative Issues
-Legislation & Legislators-South Africa
Series IX. Committees & Boards
-Trustees, Board of-Finance Committee (for material re scholarships)
-Trustees, Board of-Investor Responsibility (restriced material)
This collection is organized into eighteen series:
I. Biography
II. Academic Departments
III. Academic Programs
IV. Administrative Issues
V. Administrative Offices
VI. Alumnae
VII. Buildings and Grounds
VIII. Colleges and Universities
IX. Committees & Boards
X. Engagements
XI. Events
XII. Faculty and Staff
XIII. Graduate Work
XIV. Intercollegiate Associations
XV. Non-Smith Organizations
XVI. Speeches
XVII. Students
XVIII. Photographs
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
Half of the collection (99 document boxes, or 41 linear feet) is open to researchers according to the regulations of the College Archives. Another 99 document boxes (41 linear feet) are currently open only to employees of the office of origin.
Additions to the Collection
The Records of the Office of the President constitute a continuing collection, because certain materials remain in active use by the office for periods exceeding a president's actual tenure. The College Archives may receive accessions/additions long after the date of creation.
History of the Collection
The majority of the Dunn Files were transferred to the College Archives from the Office of the President in a number of accessions dating from the time of her tenure until the present. Some material, however, came from Dunn herself after her departure in 1995. Additional biographical materials, such as newspaper clippings, press releases, and photographs, have been added by the College Archives staff.
Search Terms
Dunn, Mary Maples.; Smith College--Presidents.; Smith College. Office of President.
Additional Information
Related Material
Additional material in the Smith College Archives about the Dunn era may be found in the records of other departments and offices of the college, as well as in the personal papers of Mary Maples Dunn.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHY, (3 document boxes / linear feet 1.3)
  The records in this series include newspaper clippings, press releases, and correspondence relating to Dunn's appointment, presidency and retirement. There is also information about her husband, Richard Dunn. More extensive biographical material can be found in Mary Maples Dunn's personal papers.
  - Appointment (Box 1)
    - -General 1985 (Box 1)
    - -Congratulations
      - -Response Sets 1985 (Box 1)
      - -Bryn Mawr Alumnae 1985 (Box 1)
      - -Bryn Mawr Faculty & Staff 1985 (Box 1)
      - -College Presidents 1985 (Box 1)
      - -Five Colleges and Northampton 1985 (Box 1)
      - -Haverford, Swarthmore and Franklin & Marshall 1985 (Box 1)
      - -Pennsylvania Friends and Neighbors 1985 (Box 1)
      - -Pennsylvania University and Government 1985 (Box 1)
      - -Personal 1985 (Box 1)
      - -Professional Engagements 1985 (Box 1)
      - -Professional Miscellaneous 1985 (Box 1)
      - -Smith College Alumnae 1985 (Box 1)
      - -Smith College Faculty & Staff 1985 (Box 1)
      - -Smith College Miscellaneous 1985 (Box 1)
      - -William & Mary 1985 (Box 1)
      - -Miscellaneous 1985 (Box 1)
      - -Miscellaneous without Response Checklists 1985-1986 (Box 1)
    - -Preparations
      - -General (Box 1)
      - -Subject Files
        - -General 1985 (Box 1)
        - -General Briefing Mat'l Prepared by JKC, Folder 1 June 1985 (Box 2)
        - -General Briefing Mat'l Prepared by JKC, Folder 2 June 1985 (Box 2)
        - -Administrative Structure 1984 (Box 2)
        - -Admissions 1985 (Box 2)
        - -Alumnae 1985 (Box 2)
        - -Budget 1985 (Box 2)
        - -Chapel 1985 (Box 2)
        - -Computing 1985 (Box 2)
        - -Curriculum 1985 (Box 2)
        - -Dean of the College 1985 (Box 2)
        - -Faculty 1985 (Box 2)
        - -Five Colleges and Northampton 1984-1985 (Box 2)
        - -President's Committee 1985 (Box 2)
        - -Project on Women and Social Change 1985 (Box 2)
        - -Sabbaticals, Leaves and Early Retirement 1984-1985 (Box 2)
        - -School for Social Work 1985 (Box 2)
        - -Triennial Reviews 1985 (Box 2)
      - -Visits
        - -6-7 Dec 1984 1984 (Box 2)
        - -11-13 Mar 1985 1985 (Box 2)
  - Curriculum Vitae 1985-1994 (Box 2)
  - Family 1988-1993 (Box 2)
  - Official Portrait 1989-1995 (Box 3)
  - Publicity
    - -Articles by MMD 1986-1987 (Box 3)
    - -Interviews
      - -General 1985-1995 (Box 3)
      - -Initiatives 1989-1990 (Box 3)
    - -Newspaper Clippings 1985-1988 (Box 3)
    - -Newspaper Clippings 1989-1995 (Box 3)
    - -Newspaper Clippings 1996-1999 (Box 3)
    - -Press Releases 1986-1993 (Box 3)
    - -Requests for Photographs ca 1985-1995 (Box 3)
  - Retirement
    - -General 1995 (Box 3)
    - -Congratulations, Folder 1 1995 (Box 3)
    - -Congratulations, Folder 2 1995 (Box 3)
    - -Dunn Celebration Day 1995 (Box 3)
    - -Student Farewells and Congratulations 1994-1995 (Box 3)
    - -Miscellaneous ca 1985-1995 (Box 3)
- SERIES II. ACADEMIC DEPARTMENTS, (3 document boxes / 1.3 linear feet)
  The files in this series are arranged alphabetically by the most recent name of the department.
  Included are newspaper clippings, correspondence, and reports from the undergraduate departments of the college. Also included are programs administered by the departments. For example, files from the Smith College Campus School are included as a sub-series of the Department of Education. However, undergraduate and graduate academic programs administered either jointly by two or more departments, or by a separate and autonomous college office, are filed either with Academic Programs or Administrative Offices. Graduate Programs are filed in the Graduate Work series. Information about Five College joint academic programs in several areas of study can be found in the Intercollegiate Associations series.
  - Afro-American Studies-Search Committee 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Art 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Art 1988-1990, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Athletics (Box 1)
    See also Series XVII. Students-Athletics
  - Classical Languages & Literature 1989, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Computer Science 1985-1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Dance 1988,1994 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - East Asian Languages & Literature 1989 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Economics 1989, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Education & Child Study
    - -General 1985-1994 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - -Campus School 1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - -Campus School 1986 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - -Campus School 1987 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - -Campus School 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - -Campus School 1990 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - -Campus School 1991-1994, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - English 1985-1991 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Exercise & Sport Studies 1985-1990 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    See also Series IX. Committees & Boards-Committee to Review the Athletic Dept. and the Dept. of Exercise and Sport Studies
  - Exercise & Sport Studies 1991-1993 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - French 1985-1993 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - German 1990 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Government 1989 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - History
    - -General 1985-1995 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - -Studies in History 1987 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Italian 1989 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Mathematics 1990 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Music
    - -General 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - -General 1987-1992 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - -General 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - -Suzuki Institute 1985-1990 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Philosophy 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Psychology 1990 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Religion & Biblical Literature 1985-1993 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Russian Language & Literature 1991 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Sciences
    - -General 1985-1992 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - -Biology 1990 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - -Chemistry 1990 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - -Geology 1990, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Sociology & Anthropology 1985, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Spanish & Portuguese 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Theatre
    - -General 1985-1989 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - -General 1990-1992 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - -Cultural Images Group 1988 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - -Women's Summer Theatre Institute 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- SERIES III. ACADEMIC PROGRAMS, (2 document boxes / 0.8 linear feet)
  The Academic Programs series consists of correspondence, newspaper clippings, and reports regarding academic programs administered by the college outside of the regular operations of academic departments. Those programs include the Ada Comstock Scholars Program, Junior Year Abroad, Bridge Program, Community College Connections, and several interdisciplinary programs.The Subject Guide provides references to funding sources for a number of this programs.
  - Ada Comstock Scholars 1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    See also Series VII. Buildings & Grounds-Dewey
  - Ada Comstock Scholars 1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ada Comstock Scholars 1987 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ada Comstock Scholars 1988 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ada Comstock Scholars 1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ada Comstock Scholars 1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ada Comstock Scholars 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ada Comstock Scholars Jan-May, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ada Comstock Scholars Jun-Dec, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Ada Comstock Scholars 1995 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bridge Program 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bridge Program 1988-1993 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Community College Connections 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Community College Connections 1993-1995 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - English as a Second Language 1990 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Film Studies 1986-1990 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Jewish Studies
    - -General 1986-1990 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - -Liv Ullman 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Junior Year Abroad
    - -General 1985-1991 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - -Apartments 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - -Financial Aid 1986-1991 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - -Gulf War 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - -France 1985-1987, 1990, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - -Geneva 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - -Hamburg 1986-1991 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - -Italy 1986-1990, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - -Kyoto 1989-1994 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - -Thailand 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - -Third World 1987 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Latin American Studies 1987 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Peace & War Studies 1987 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Preludes 1991 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Public Policy 1987, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - STRIDE 1994 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Women's Studies 1986-1990, 1992, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- SERIES IV. ADMINISTRATIVE ISSUES, (11 document boxes / 4.6 linear feet)
  This series documents activity in the President's Office which is either of a general nature, requiring the attention of only the president and her closest assistants, or requiring the participation of a number of administrative bodies at once. Included in this series are records relating to a number of general issues, such as Legislators and Legislation, Lesbianism, Race, and Women's Education. At the end of the series there is a collection of miscellaneous correspondence handled by the President's Office, filed in chronological order. Several issues, such as lesbianism, race and South Africa divestment, pervaded many areas of campus activity. Because material on these topics can be found under a variety of headings, a Subject Guide has been provided on pages 9-11 of this finding aid to assist the researcher.
  - Administrative Processes, Office Methods Ltd. Report 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Administrative Structure 1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Affirmative Action (Box 1)
    See Subject Guide for sources of information
  - AIDS (Box 1)
    See Series IX. Committees & Boards-AIDS Committees
  - Calendar
    - -General 1985-1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - -General 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - -Appointment Books 1989-1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Curriculum 1987-1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Diversity
    - -Equity Institute
      See also Series V. Administrative Offices-Development-Foundations-Hazen
      - -General 1986 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - -General Jan-May 1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - -General Jun-Dec 1987 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - -General 1988-1992, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - -Reports 1986 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - -Reports Mar-Jul 1987 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - -Reports Sep-Nov 1987 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - -Reports 1988 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - -Smith Design
      - -General 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - -Memoranda 1988 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - -Implementation 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - -GTE Focus Grant 1988 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - -Call to Action
        - -Final Mar 1989 (Box 2, Folder 8)
        - -Drafts Jul 1988 (Box 2, Folder 9)
        - -Drafts Aug 1988 (Box 2, Folder 10)
        - -Drafts Sep 1988 (Box 3, Folder 1)
        - -Drafts Oct 1988 (Box 3, Folder 2)
        - -Background Material and Notes 1988 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - -Data on Minority Students 1988 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - -Report Requests [1 of 2] Jun 1989 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - -Report Requests [2 of 2] Jun 1989 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - -Responses 1988, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Email (Box 3)
    See Series IX Committees & Boards-Senior Staff for series of meeting agendas and background information in late 1993 and 1994
  - Flag Lowering 1992 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Kirkpatrick, Jeane 1987-1989 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Legal Counsel
    - -General 1985-1993 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - -Justice Department Investigation 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Legislation and Legislators
    - -General 1985 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - -General 1986 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - -General 1987 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - -General 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - -General 1990-1991 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - -General 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - -General 1994-1995 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - -Conte, Silvio 1988-1994 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - -Senate Committee on Commerce, Science and Technology 1988 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - -Science Advisory Committees 1990, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - -South Africa 1985-1986, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Lesbianism
    See Subject Guide for further sources of information
    - -General 1985-1990 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - -General 1991-1993, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - -Feminist and Lesbian Alumnae of Smith 1985-1990 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - -Information Packet Jan 1992 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Mailing Lists and Delivery 1991 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Martin Luther King, Jr.'s Birthday, Observance of (Box 5)
    See Series IX. Committees & Boards-Senior Staff, for 6 March 1990 staff meeting agenda.
  - Master Plan (Box 5)
    See Series IX. Committees & Boards-Campus Committee and Series IX. Committees & Boards-College Planning & Resources, Committee on
  - Media Coverage
    - -General 1986-1995 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - -The New York Times 1986-1990 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - -U.S. News and World Report 1987-1988 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - -U.S. News and World Report 1989-1994 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Nuclear War 1985-1986 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Persian Gulf War 1991 (Box 5, Folder 15)